<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bowles Lab, UC Berkeley on Bowles Lab, UC Berkeley</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Bowles Lab, UC Berkeley on Bowles Lab, UC Berkeley</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2016 Timothy Bowles</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Aidee Guzman</title>
      <link>/group_members/aidee-guzman/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/group_members/aidee-guzman/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am a Ph.D. candidate at UC Berkeley in the Department of Environmental Science, Policy, and Management in both Dr. Claire Kremen’s and Dr. Timothy Bowles’s labs. Having deep family roots in agriculture, I am compelled to understand the socio-ecological linkages of diversified farming systems. My research builds on the knowledge produced in ecology, soil microbiology, pollination biology, and sociology of agriculture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my dissertation, I am working with small-scale farmers embedded in the monoculture landscape of California&amp;rsquo;s Central Valley. My research explores how on-farm diversification practices impact soil health and link to other ecological processes (i.e. pollination) on agroecosystems. Specifically, I am looking at how on-farm diversification (i.e. crop diversity over space and time) influence arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi (AMF), pollination, and their interactions. Throughout my research, I aim to integrate social and ecological research approaches to support farmers, rural livelihoods, and ecological resilience.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yvonne Socolar</title>
      <link>/group_members/yvonne-socolar/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/group_members/yvonne-socolar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yvonne is a PhD student in the Department of Environmental Science, Policy and Management at Berkeley. From farm labor on smallholder vegetable operations to food stamps outreach to baking professionally, Yvonne’s career before grad school traced food from healthy soils to healthy communities. Her research interests now lie at the agriculture-environment-health nexus, and she studies how agricultural practices that promote farms’ ecological health can be employed to improve crops’ nutritional quality, particularly in the face of climate change. Prior to Berkeley, Yvonne received a BA in Biology from Swarthmore College and an MS in Agriculture, Food and Environment from Tufts University.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Addressing agricultural nitrogen losses in a changing climate</title>
      <link>/publication/bowles-et-al-2018-ns/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/bowles-et-al-2018-ns/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mycorrhizal fungi enhance plant nutrient acquisition and modulate nitrogen loss with variable water regimes</title>
      <link>/publication/bowles-et-al-2017-gcb/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/bowles-et-al-2017-gcb/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Agroecological solutions for climate challenges</title>
      <link>/project/agroecology-and-climate/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/agroecology-and-climate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Water availability in California and across much of the world will become increasingly scarce and variable as climate change affects precipitation patterns and urban residents use more available water. We study the implications of these changes for crop productivity and environmental pollution, particularly how agroecological approaches can help address challenges. Ongoing work, funded by a USDA AFRI Foundational grant, examines how crop rotational diversity affect soil health and the soil microbiome, and in turn, the extent to which more diverse rotations suffer fewer yield losses in more stressful conditions. A related synthesis/review project examines how nitrogen losses from agricultural systems may worsen with climate change-driven changes in precipitation patterns, and how agrocological approaches at multiple scales will be key to mitigating these losses, rather than just fertilizer management.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ansel Klein</title>
      <link>/group_members/ansel-klein/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/group_members/ansel-klein/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My research interests lie at the intersection of soil science, agroecology, and spatial science. Using quantitative biogeochemical approaches and social science research methods, I seek to link how specific management regimes of organic farmers in Yolo County, California reflect measured and perceived impacts to on-farm soil health.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coleman Rainey</title>
      <link>/group_members/coleman-rainey/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/group_members/coleman-rainey/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Cole is pursuing a PhD in the Materials Science and Engineering Department with a focus on biogeochemical cycling governed by nanophase particles in soil systems. Studying complexation of organics and nutrients by clay minerals using Cryo-TEM, XRD, and other spectroscopic methods, Cole hopes to uncover how clays act as reactive sites for microbial metabolism and nutrient exchange in soils. In addition, iron oxyhydroxides nanoparticles have high sorption capacities for metal contaminants and govern dispersal and remediation processes. Using atomic resolution HRTEM, Cole hopes to discover the complex surface crystal structures that mediate arsenic, chromium, mercury, lead, and selenium sorption, with an ultimate focus on bioavailability and transport kinetics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He is a member of Jillian Banfield&amp;rsquo;s lab and affiliated with the Bowles lab through his interest in urban agroecology and soil processes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Maria Mooshammer</title>
      <link>/group_members/maria-mooshammer/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/group_members/maria-mooshammer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Microbes are key players in the global carbon and nutrient cycles, and the engines of ecosystem
functions. My research focuses on understanding how microbial communities control soil carbon and
nutrient cycling in both natural and agricultural systems, as well as their stability and resilience to climate changes. I am particularly interested in soil organic nitrogen cycling, the regulation of carbon and nitrogen cycling through adjustments in microbial community physiology (microbial carbon and nitrogen use efficiency), and the coupling of microbial carbon, nitrogen and phosphorus cycling during organic matter decomposition. I use a vast range of methods to study soil biogeochemical processes, and I have particular experience in stable isotope-based approaches.
Over the past years, I have become increasingly interested in soil health, particularly in the context of soil fertility and sustainable agriculture. At the Bowles Lab, I am currently investigating how crop rotational diversity affects the plant-soil-microbe interactions that underlie beneficial microbiomes and soil health, and how in turn they contribute to greater resilience of crop productivity to droughts and heat waves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.at/citations?user=rdK7vq0AAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Maria&amp;rsquo;s Google Scholar profile&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rhizosphere ecology</title>
      <link>/project/rhizosphere-ecology/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/rhizosphere-ecology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The rhizosphere is the hotspot of biological activity in and around plant roots. Addressing some of the biggest challenges in agricultural systems, such as enhancing nutrient and water cycling to improve resource use, depend on better understanding and management of rhizosphere processes. Arbuscular mycorrhizas (AM) are an ancient and near-ubiquitous association between plant roots and a specialized group of soil fungi that facilitate nutrient uptake and other functions in exchange for energy. We use a variety of approaches to study this symbiotic interaction &lt;em&gt;in situ&lt;/em&gt;, often using a tomato model system with paired AM and non-AM genotypes. Recent and ongoing work has focused on how AM fungi affect plants and ecosystem processes, especially nitrogen cycling and losses, under lower and more variable water regimes (Bowles et al., 2016 &lt;em&gt;STOTEN&lt;/em&gt;, Bowles et al., 2017 &lt;em&gt;Global Change Biology&lt;/em&gt;). We also recently completed a meta-analysis showing how cover cropping and lower intensity tillage have similar, positive effects on the extent to which AM fungi colonize cash crop roots, a proxy of potential function (Bowles et al., 2016 &lt;em&gt;Journal of Applied Ecology&lt;/em&gt;). Other ongoing work focuses on how long-term plant-soil feedbacks affect belowground processes during drought, by studying the effects of crop rotational diversity on microbial community structure and function and plant-soil-microbe interactions under stress.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>S. Franz Bender</title>
      <link>/group_members/franz-bender/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/group_members/franz-bender/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Soils harbor enormous biodiversity. We are just beginning to understand how soil organisms and
their diversity contribute to the functioning of ecosystems. Moreover, evidence is increasing that human soil management can have adverse effects on soil biological communities and,
potentially, also the functions they provide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My research focusses on disentangling the complex relationships between agricultural
management, soil biological communities and ecosystem functions. I’m especially interested in
identifying ways to integrate soil biologically provided ecosystem services into agricultural
management schemes, an approach termed ‘Soil Ecological Engineering’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use a combination of field and greenhouse experimentation to understand the functional
potential of the different members of soil biological communities and to assess how these
functional implications change under different management systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While my research covers a range of different soil organisms, I particularly focus on plant
symbiotic arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi, their interactions with the wider soil food web and how these affect nutrient use efficiency and crop nutrition in agricultural systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.ch/citations?user=JSPnu1EAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Franz&amp;rsquo;s Google Scholar profile&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Soil health and ecosystem services</title>
      <link>/project/soil-health/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/soil-health/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Restoring and maintaining soil health are essential to making agriculture viable in the long-term. Soil health describes the dynamic properties of soil that can be changed by management, especially soil organic matter, soil biota, and chemical characteristics like pH. Thus soil health is distinct from intrinsic soil characteristics like texture, although these factors strongly influence soil health. The metaphor of &amp;ldquo;health&amp;rdquo; implies that soils can range from a &amp;ldquo;diseased&amp;rdquo; state to a &amp;ldquo;healthy&amp;rdquo; state, the latter marked by an active and diverse biological community and stable or increasing levels of soil organic matter that support key ecological functions like nutrient cycling and retention, water infiltration and storage, pest suppression, productivity with minimal nonrenewable inputs, and ultimately, resilience to stress. Yet intensively-managed agricultural systems mainly create sickly soils. Broadly, we are interested in how farmers&amp;rsquo; innovations restore and maintain soil health, and the ecological consequences of doing so. Through collaborations with social scientists and environmental policy experts, we are also interested in barriers, opportunities, and enabling conditions for adopting practices that support soil health. Previous research with organic farmers in Yolo Co., California, investigated how farmers could achieve high yields and low potential for nitrogen losses (Bowles et al, 2014, &lt;em&gt;Soil Biology and Biochemistry&lt;/em&gt;, Bowles et al, 2015, &lt;em&gt;PLoS ONE&lt;/em&gt;, Margenot et al., 2015 &lt;em&gt;SSSAJ&lt;/em&gt;). High levels of total and labile soil organic matter were a key feature of farms that could achieve both. New interdisciplinary research will focus on the Central Coast region of California, America&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Salad Bowl&amp;rdquo; and a statewide assessment of soil health barriers and opportunities lead by &lt;a href=&#34;https://ourenvironment.berkeley.edu/people/alastair-t-iles&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Alastair Iles&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://food.berkeley.edu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Berkeley Food Institute&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Example Talk</title>
      <link>/talk/example-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/example-talk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Embed your slides or video here using &lt;a href=&#34;https://gcushen.github.io/hugo-academic-demo/post/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;shortcodes&lt;/a&gt;. Further details can easily be added using &lt;em&gt;Markdown&lt;/em&gt; and $\rm \LaTeX$ math code.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ecological intensification and arbuscular mycorrhizas: a meta-analysis of tillage and cover crop effects</title>
      <link>/publication/bowles-et-al-2016-jae/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/bowles-et-al-2016-jae/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effects of arbuscular mycorrhizae on tomato yield, nutrient uptake, water relations, and soil carbon dynamics under deficit irrigation in field conditions</title>
      <link>/publication/bowles-et-al-2016-stoten/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/bowles-et-al-2016-stoten/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tightly-coupled plant-soil nitrogen cycling: Comparison of organic farms across an agricultural landscape</title>
      <link>/publication/bowles-et-al-2015-plos-one/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/bowles-et-al-2015-plos-one/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
