<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Group_members on Bowles Lab, UC Berkeley</title>
    <link>/group_members/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Group_members on Bowles Lab, UC Berkeley</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2016 Timothy Bowles</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/group_members/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Yvonne Socolar</title>
      <link>/group_members/yvonne-socolar/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/group_members/yvonne-socolar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yvonne is a PhD student in the Department of Environmental Science, Policy and Management at Berkeley. From farm labor on smallholder vegetable operations to food stamps outreach to baking professionally, Yvonne’s career before grad school traced food from healthy soils to healthy communities. Her research interests now lie at the agriculture-environment-health nexus, and she studies how agricultural practices that promote farms’ ecological health can be employed to improve crops’ nutritional quality, particularly in the face of climate change. Prior to Berkeley, Yvonne received a BA in Biology from Swarthmore College and an MS in Agriculture, Food and Environment from Tufts University.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ansel Klein</title>
      <link>/group_members/ansel-klein/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/group_members/ansel-klein/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My research interests lie at the intersection of soil science, agroecology, and spatial science. Using quantitative biogeochemical approaches and social science research methods, I seek to link how specific management regimes of organic farmers in Yolo County, California reflect measured and perceived impacts to on-farm soil health.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coleman Rainey</title>
      <link>/group_members/coleman-rainey/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/group_members/coleman-rainey/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Cole is pursuing a PhD in the Materials Science and Engineering Department with a focus on biogeochemical cycling governed by nanophase particles in soil systems. Studying complexation of organics and nutrients by clay minerals using Cryo-TEM, XRD, and other spectroscopic methods, Cole hopes to uncover how clays act as reactive sites for microbial metabolism and nutrient exchange in soils. In addition, iron oxyhydroxides nanoparticles have high sorption capacities for metal contaminants and govern dispersal and remediation processes. Using atomic resolution HRTEM, Cole hopes to discover the complex surface crystal structures that mediate arsenic, chromium, mercury, lead, and selenium sorption, with an ultimate focus on bioavailability and transport kinetics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He is a member of Jillian Banfield&amp;rsquo;s lab and affiliated with the Bowles lab through his interest in urban agroecology and soil processes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Maria Mooshammer</title>
      <link>/group_members/maria-mooshammer/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/group_members/maria-mooshammer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Microbes are key players in the global carbon and nutrient cycles, and the engines of ecosystem
functions. My research focuses on understanding how microbial communities control soil carbon and
nutrient cycling in both natural and agricultural systems, as well as their stability and resilience to climate changes. I am particularly interested in soil organic nitrogen cycling, the regulation of carbon and nitrogen cycling through adjustments in microbial community physiology (microbial carbon and nitrogen use efficiency), and the coupling of microbial carbon, nitrogen and phosphorus cycling during organic matter decomposition. I use a vast range of methods to study soil biogeochemical processes, and I have particular experience in stable isotope-based approaches.
Over the past years, I have become increasingly interested in soil health, particularly in the context of soil fertility and sustainable agriculture. At the Bowles Lab, I am currently investigating how crop rotational diversity affects the plant-soil-microbe interactions that underlie beneficial microbiomes and soil health, and how in turn they contribute to greater resilience of crop productivity to droughts and heat waves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.at/citations?user=rdK7vq0AAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Maria&amp;rsquo;s Google Scholar profile&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>S. Franz Bender</title>
      <link>/group_members/franz-bender/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/group_members/franz-bender/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Soils harbor enormous biodiversity. We are just beginning to understand how soil organisms and
their diversity contribute to the functioning of ecosystems. Moreover, evidence is increasing that human soil management can have adverse effects on soil biological communities and,
potentially, also the functions they provide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My research focusses on disentangling the complex relationships between agricultural
management, soil biological communities and ecosystem functions. I’m especially interested in
identifying ways to integrate soil biologically provided ecosystem services into agricultural
management schemes, an approach termed ‘Soil Ecological Engineering’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use a combination of field and greenhouse experimentation to understand the functional
potential of the different members of soil biological communities and to assess how these
functional implications change under different management systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While my research covers a range of different soil organisms, I particularly focus on plant
symbiotic arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi, their interactions with the wider soil food web and how these affect nutrient use efficiency and crop nutrition in agricultural systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.ch/citations?user=JSPnu1EAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Franz&amp;rsquo;s Google Scholar profile&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
